<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians triumph over death a sermon at the funeral of Richard Legh of Lime in the county Palatine of Chester, Esq., at Winwick in the county Palatine of Lancaster Sept. 6. 1687 / W. Shippen ...</title>
            <author>Shippen, W. (William), 1637?-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3441A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4015</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11791927</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11791927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59969)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 823:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians triumph over death a sermon at the funeral of Richard Legh of Lime in the county Palatine of Chester, Esq., at Winwick in the county Palatine of Lancaster Sept. 6. 1687 / W. Shippen ...</title>
                  <author>Shippen, W. (William), 1637?-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the theater,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Dedicatory page signed: W.S.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Legh, Richard, d. 1687.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, XV, 55 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Future life.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49240:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS <hi>Triumph over Death.</hi> A SERMON AT THE FUNERAL OF <hi>RICHARD LEGH</hi> of Lime IN THE County Palatine of CHESTER <abbr>Eſq</abbr> AT WINWICK IN THE County Palatine of LANCASTER <hi>Sept.</hi> 6. 1687.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By W. Shippen</hi> D.D. <hi>Rector of</hi> Stockport <hi>in</hi> Cheſhire, <hi>Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Fellow of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſ. Coll.</hi> Oxon.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of Sheldonian Theater</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD</hi> Printed at the THEATER 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49240:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>GILB. IRONSIDE</hi> Vice-Can. OXON.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> 12. 1688.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49240:2"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured and moſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Legh,</hi> the Vertuous Relict of <hi>Richard Legh</hi> of <hi>Lime</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAD my abilities to perform, been equal to my propenſion to undertake your commands, theſe Papers had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented you with ſomthing more worthy the memory of that half of your ſelf which is in Heaven, and leſs unfit for the peruſal of the other with which we are ſtill honoured upon Earth. But the greateſt ambition, as well as the moſt proper diſpoſal of them as they are, was to have heen buried in the ſame dark Vault with their ſubject. Yet ſeeing you would not be prevailed with to lay aſide your authority over me, nor be denied a ſight of that, which your circumſtances would not permit you to hear. I committed this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe into your hands, in confidence you would have confined it to your Cloſet; where I could
<pb facs="tcp:49240:3"/>have reſted ſecure of a pardon for all its fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lures, upon your own native goodneſs; but could never have admitted the leaſt thought of ſuffering it to be more publick, had it not been for your irreſiſtible commands, and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible reſolutions to have it ſo, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greateſt and juſteſt importunities of my ſelf and friends to the contrary; ſo that your Ladyſhip muſt be accountable to the world for the many imperfections it labours under.</p>
            <p>The Pictures of our abſent friends though they expreſs no more then their outward and viſible features are very deſireable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful monuments; but the Character of their minds, and their inward and inviſible beauties are far more excellent and valuable.</p>
            <p>Fine ſpirits like elegant faces are difficult to be drawn to an exactneſs, even by the greateſt Maſters. And this worthy perſon hath been equally unhappy both under the Pencil and the Pen. How little I have ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, and how ſhort this rude draught falls of the Original: your firſt reading (I doubt) will teſtify with trouble if not with tears: and now when 'tis too late, force you to take up my firſt wiſh that this Province had been
<pb facs="tcp:49240:3"/>allotted to a more skilful hand, that might have done him more right, and given you more ſatisfaction. Better parts might not only have ſet a greater luſtre on ſo noble a Theme, but have reflected an honour upon themſelves, and together with his conſecrated their own names to Eternity; while my humble Talent only ſues for an excuſe, and may not unreaſonably expect it too; if either extremity of Paſſion through this ſurprizing blow; or diſtraction of thought, from a like intervenient Occaſion and Office I was called to at the ſame time, which throws the mind into confuſion, and darkneſs, may paſs for indiſpoſitions to ſuch compoſures. But what ever Entertainment this diſcourſe may meet with from its deficiencies of form, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of art, in this nice and cenſorions age, yet the richneſs of the matter, and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the argument are ſufficient (I know) to recommend it to a place among your choic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Cimelia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as the greatneſs of his worth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hances the eſtimate of your loſs; ſo the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing of that, doth but open and revive your ſenſe of this: which I finding it more
<pb facs="tcp:49240:4"/>reaſonable to appeaſe then aggravate, and obſerving how much you reſemble the famous Lady <hi>Paulina</hi> in S. <hi>Jerom</hi> not only in the eminence of her Vertues, but in the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her paſſions; ſhall rather recommend to you thoſe few familier conſiderations in the cloſe hereof directed to the ſtopping of the ſtream of nature; or allaying the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs of your grief, if not the turning it into the ſweeter paſſion of Joy. To the making all which advices of reaſon, and ſuccours of faith there offered, effectual to that purpoſe, 'tis requiſite that you bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with you, a ſerious attention, and a greatneſs of Spirit: The former of which you have in your power, the latter in your nature. For the awakening of which, I know nothing more prevalent then to mind you of the original Stock, from whence you Sprung; and of thoſe perſonal qualifications, and that elevated Genius, wherewith you are bleſſed. Your paternal family hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out perſons of that eminence both for parts and virtues, as have adorned the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtations in Church and State. A delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate reflection whereupon will hardly ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:49240:4"/>you to ſtoop to ſo weak a paſſion, or entertain ſo mean a thought, as muſt ſink you below the dignity of your <hi>Line,</hi> or to be dejected with any thing, ſave what is degenerous, or inglorious. Your own excellent endowments which have ſufficiently appeared on other occaſions; as the ſerenity of your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the ſoundneſs of your Judgment and conſtancy of mind, if duly touched and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited with theſe meditations can hardly fail of raiſing the deſired effects. But though envy it ſelf cannot but give place to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence for the dead; yet it will not ſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently brook the commendations of the living. And though his modeſty who is gone cannot be wounded by his Juſt Character, yet yours is ſo tender, that it would be oppreſſed with your own. So that I know not how to do right to the reſt of your Vertues, without offering an injury to this. I ſhall therefore indeavour to ſupply the omiſſion of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved praiſes, and the weakneſs of my other performances, with the ſincerity and ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of my prayers, to him who can <hi>wipe all tears from your Eyes, and make the bones that he hath broken to rejoyce,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49240:5"/>for your ſupport and improvement under this ſevere Viſitation; that what you have loſt in temporal comforts, may be abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed you in Spiritual, in this life; and with eternal glory in the next: which ſhall be the conſtant Interceſſion of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured Madam</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient Faithful, Humble ſervant W. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. <hi>3. 1687.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49240:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. XV. 55.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>O Death! where is thy Sting? O Grave! where is thy Victory?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE words at the firſt view, may ſeem but an improper ſubject for this ſad and ſolemn occaſion. For what greater ſoloe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm can well be imagined, than a Text of rejoycing for a Funeral Sermon? than the celebrating a Day of mourning and lamentation with a ſong of Triumph? and the drawing the bright ſcene of Mirth, and Jubilee, before the clouded minds of the diſconſolate and afflicted? What an incongruity to ask, where are the weapons of Death, and where's the Victory of the Grave, when every place and object, proclaims their puiſſance and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements? Every Church yard and Charnel-houſe being ſtuffd with their ſpoils; and the whole earth but one <hi>Mackpelah,</hi> where they beſtow their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and bury their ſlain. The cries of the Mourners that go about the ſtreets, and the tears of them that weep within doors, do ſufficiently confeſs the wounds, and acknowledge the conqueſts of theſe powerful enemies. And the ſad ſpectacle before us, being already the Triumph of the one, and ſuddenly to become the Captive of the other; ſeems at once to anſwer the Queſtion, and defeat
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49240:6"/>the Inſultation of the Text. So that might it not have been better ſaid, <hi>O Death! where is</hi> not <hi>thy Sting? O Grave! where is</hi> not <hi>thy Victory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all this, he that looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words with ſenſes duely exerciſed, may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne a great propriety in them for the preſent Solemnity: and by Faith, as through a <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> diſcover a Rich and pleaſant Country beyond the Gloomy region of the Grave, and a freſh Bloom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life ſpringing out of the Duſt of Death. Which though it bears the name of an Enemy, yet to a good Chriſtian performs the Office of a Friend, in letting him out of this vain and wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed State of Mortality into a life of unmixt, and unchangeable Glory. This contemplation hath force enough not only to Juſtify the ſuitableneſs of the Text, but to reform our common Sentiments and practices upon ſuch occaſions, by making us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change our Cypreſs for Laurel, and our tears of Sorrow for thoſe of Joy, which will farther ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear upon a due examination of theſe words.</p>
            <p>This Text I have taken at the ſecond hand; it being not Originally the Apoſtles (as himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes in the verſe preceding) but a Quotation of his out of the Prophet <hi>Hoſea, c.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 14. which place though our Tranſlation reading thus, <hi>O Death! I will be thy Plagues; O Grave! I will be thy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;</hi> gives but a faint reſemblance to it. Yet the Septuagint comes nearer to it, eſpecially if we allow the Words <hi>Sting</hi> and <hi>Victory</hi> to have been tranſpoſed through the tranſcribers negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; which is favoured by conſiderable
<note n="a" place="margin">Beza &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iorum.</note> Copies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49240:6"/>and
<note n="b" place="margin">Vulgar Aethiopic.</note> Verſions retaining the Prophets order of the words in this paſſage of the Apoſtle, For then they would be found to differ only in one word, and not at all in ſenſe, it being to the ſame effect whether we ſay <hi>O Grave! where is thy Victory?</hi> or, <hi>where is thy Cauſe?</hi> wherein thou haſt ſo long prevailed. Or, <hi>where is thy Plea</hi> which thou uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to put in at the Bar of Divine Juſtice? as for the word which we here render [I will
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> be] it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſignifies the ſame with that which is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſlated [
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Where] in the Judgment of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Eminent Chriſtian
<note n="e" place="margin">Jun. and Tremel. &amp;c.</note> Interpreters, and of ſome learned Jews, as well as of the Septuagint, which here, and generally where not corrupted, is our beſt Guide to the true ſenſe of the Original, and for that reaſon alone, doubtleſs, was ſo often fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Inſpired Pen-men of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, even when it ſeemingly departs from the preſent reading of the Hebrew Code, (ſo that
<note n="f" place="margin">Capell. Critic. Sacr.</note> their conjecture is as needleſs, as 'tis groundleſs, who conceive the latter Hebrew word was read by the LXX in this place, inſtead of the former.) But the Hebrew it ſelf hath the greateſt affinity of all with the Text, according to ſome; and thoſe moſt
<note n="g" place="margin">Dr. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock on this place.</note> eminently learned in the Oriental Tongues; by whoſe aſſiſtance they have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to reconcile and adjuſt all the reſt of the words, both as to their Signification and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of place; and ſo completed the agreement betwixt the Prophet and the Apoſtle. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that be, 'tis ſufficient for our purpoſe, that the ſenſe of the two clauſes in this ſentence,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49240:7"/>is not much different; and the ſcope of the whole, even in our verſion, is exactly the ſame. <hi>O Death where are thy</hi> fatal <hi>Plagues?</hi> or poiſonons <hi>Sting; O Grave! where is thy deſtruction</hi> of, or <hi>Victory</hi> gained over them.</p>
            <p>Which Words though in the Prophet they might literally denote Gods deliverance of his people from the greateſt temporal Dangers and Enemies even Death and the Grave, and which by ſome
<note n="h" place="margin">Grotius in loc.</note> are applyed to Gods deſtruction of <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> Army; yet by the Apoſtle they are raiſed to an higher ſenſe, and adapted to the general Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: when <hi>Death</hi> and the Grave <hi>ſhall be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in Victory.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> i. e. for ever, when they ſhall be quite Aboliſhed, and Vaniſh; not only ſo, as to be no more, but ſo as no Footſteps ſhall remain of their having ever been; when there ſhall not be ſeen ſo much as the leaſt Marks, or Scars up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe who have layn under their utmoſt Force and Cruelty; not a Blemiſh on their Bodies, nor a Hair of their heads Singed.</p>
            <p>And as this Scripture will then have its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation, ſo it certainly had its Beginning at Chriſts Reſurrection; when the groundwork was laid of this our Rejoycing. Whereupon theſe words are conceived by ſome to have been a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>the Captain of our Salvation,</hi> when having foiled his Enemies, wreſted their Weapons out of their hands, given them their Deaths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wound, and ſeeing them ly grovelling upon the ground, he might draw near, and Inſult them ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>where's now thy Sting, O! Death?</hi> wherewith
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49240:7"/>thou haſt ſo often wounded and poiſoned man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind? <hi>Where's now thy Victory, O Grave!</hi> which thou haſt ſo long carried, and boaſted of, over the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men. And the Apoſtle here under the certain hope, and ſweet contemplation of that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious day of Univerſal Triumph cannot for bear to anticipate that joy of the Reſurrection: but look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon theſe baffled enemies, a ſtingleſs Death, and a powerleſs Grave, as hurtleſs and deſpicable things; breaks out into this Triumphant ſong; this holy Exaltation and Inſultation of the Text. <hi>O Death!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe words imply a Complete Victory, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a Joyful Triumph. The better to repreſent the reaſonableneſs of which Triumph, and to lay bare the Foundations of this Rejoycing, we muſt enquire what Victory this is, and by whom obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but before we can learn its juſt value and greatneſs, we muſt be acquainted with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality of the Adverſary: ſo that we have three parts or ſteps cut out for the progreſs of our Diſcourſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Nature and Dreadfulneſs of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author and Abſoluteneſs of the Victory over them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Reaſonableneſs of Triumphing, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing for the ſame.</p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to the firſt part, we ſhall ſhew 1. Who and what kind of Enemies theſe are.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49240:8"/>2. With what Weapon they aſſail us. 3. What Succeſs they have formerly had.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Enemies are Death, and the Grave. That by the former is here meant the death of the Body, is manifeſt from the whole bent and ſcope of this Chapter; which is to demonſtrate the Reſurrection of the dead; both of Chriſt the firſt fruits, and of all Chriſtians as the entire har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, through him at his coming. And it is thence alſo no leſs evident, that by Grave (though the Original Word both in the Prophet and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, by its various and doubtful ſenſes, hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded a large field to the Criticks to ſhew their Reading and Judgement in) is here to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, neither the Priſon of the damned, nor the ſtate of the dead, but the Manſion of our Carkaſſes till the Reſurrection: And though Death and the Grave are here diſtinguiſhed by the Apoſtle, yet in effect being the ſame to us, we ſhall in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele of this diſcourſe, for the moſt part, ſpeak of them as but One.</p>
            <p>This is the enemy then we have to deal with, and how <hi>Dreadful</hi> it is to the Children of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption needs no other proof, than a bare appeal to the Univerſal ſenſe and ſuffrage of mankind;
<note place="margin">Job. 18.14.</note> which <hi>Job</hi> hath roundly ſumm'd up in his deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Death by <hi>the King of terrours:</hi> and after him <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> much to the ſame purpoſe, in ſtyling it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. There's nothing in the World can beget a greater dread, or create a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite horrour in the minds of men, than the black and Melancholly apprehenſion of deſcending into
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49240:8"/>the diſmal ſtate of everlaſting darkneſs and ſolitude; oblivion and ſenſleſneſs. There's nothing we are not willing to do, to ſuffer, or to part with, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than be brought under its power. We are ready to undergo all labours and pains, faſting and Phyſick, ſhame and tortures, nay (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid) death it ſelf to avoid it. So much of truth is there in That of the Father of lies; <hi>Skin for Skin, and all that a man hath,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 2.4.</note> will be give for his Life.</hi> And this is ſo well grounded a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that it ſeizes and ſhakes the mind, and ſhri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels up the Spirits of the ſtouteſt, the wiſeſt, and moſt virtuous men. Our natures are agaſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coil at the very thoughts of death, and our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances wax wan at the ſight of the Grave. We are ſo unfit to enter the liſts with theſe Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, that we are ſcarce able to ſupport our ſelves under the bare proſpect or mention of them. Theſe <hi>Baſilisks</hi> diſ-ſpirit us at their approach, and kill us with their very looks. The ſound of their names (like that of <hi>Hunniades</hi> to the <hi>Turks</hi>) ſtrikes a dread into our Soul, and ſhoots a chilneſs through our Veins: which <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11th was ſo appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of, that he would not endure the menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, either in health or ſickneſs; but charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Servants when ever they ſhould ſee him weak and languiſhing, to exhort him to confeſs his Sins, but in no wiſe to name death to him, leaſt that alone ſhould kill him before the time. The reaſon of all which muſt be ſought for, in our Inbred Antipathy to Annihilation. The fear of Death lies as cloſe to our eſſence as the Love
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49240:9"/>of Life, and to offer to reconcile a man to the thoughts of his diſſolution, is as contradictory an attempt, as to perſwade him to fall out with his nature, and renounce his being: And if it be a Natural, it muſt alſo be a Neceſſary, and unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſion: and conſequently 'tis as impoſſible to throw off the Fear, as the Fate of dying.</p>
            <p>This Enemy is not only Formidable, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative meerly upon the fancy, but its really Hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and <hi>Miſchievous.</hi> Death ſmites us in all our Capacities, in our Relations, and our Perſons. It turns us out of our Statelieſt Houſes and Palaces; and Sequeſters us from our greateſt poſſeſſions and Empires. It blaſts our faireſt Hopes, and daſhes in pieces our fineſt Models: <hi>Breaking our purpoſes, and the thoughts of our heart.</hi> It ſnatches our tender Children out of our Arms, and tears away the deareſt Gueſt of our boſom from us. It plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders us of our beauty and our ſtrength, of our honours and our pleaſures. It not only deprives us of our liberty and the light, by ſhutting us up in a cloſe dark priſon; but it layeth us in a bed of diſhonour and loathſomneſs among worms and ſerpents. It throws us into a Pit of ſtench and rottenneſs; where it preys upon our bodies, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefies our fleſh, and conſumes our bones. It not only lops off ſome of our choiceſt comforts; but lays the Ax to the root of all our Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; in making a divorce betwixt the deareſt Couple in nature, our Body and Soul; and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after it (if not timely prevented) an utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of both eternally.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49240:9"/>
            <p>Add hereunto, that this is an inveterate and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable</hi> Enemy: with whom there can no league be ſtruck, no amity purchaſed, no reconciliation had. It gives quarter to none; but ſhews the like mercy of the Sword to all. Indeed beaten, captivated, deſtroy'd it may be, (ſo it hath been by Chriſt) but appeaſed, reconciled, never. The Devil who is General and Parent of this Enemy, being the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Sin, (who is the Mother of Death) hath like an infernal <hi>Hannibal</hi> ſworn all his Offspring to have no peace with the Poſterity of <hi>Adam.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs Death could do us no great miſchief, if he came not armed with his Sting, which is</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular: the weapon with which this Enemy aſſaults us. The meaning and reaſon of which Title is next to be examined. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle declares the former briefly and plainly in the next words. <hi>The ſting of death is ſin.</hi> A dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deadly weapon. The congruity of their names might be deduced from their common rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a Serpent; whoſe natural weapon is a ſting, as Sin is the proper hurtful Inſtrument of that old Serpent, the Devil. But the dreadfulneſs of this Weapon, and its analogy to a Sting, will more fully appear from a diſtinct conſideration of the Pungent and Poiſonous nature of Sin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sin is of a Pungent and Painful nature; It uſually approaches us indeed with a courtly addreſs, and a fawning ſalutation: like <hi>Solomons</hi> ſtrange Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; her <hi>lips drop as an hony comb, and her mouth is ſmoother than oil: but the end is bitter as wormwood, ſharp as a two edged ſword.</hi> A proſperous and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49240:10"/>Sinner, (who reſolves to go on <hi>in the way of his heart, and in the ſight of his eyes</hi>) knowing what ſmart and anguiſh the reflection upon his guilt, and the very thoughts of the Divine Vengeance will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily give him, induſtriouſly beats out of his mind all notices and remembrances of theſe things; and bears down the firſt eſſays of Conſcience, either to inform or reſtrain him. The <hi>Voluptuary</hi> indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to drown its voice with the louder noiſe of his Tabret and Harp. The <hi>Mammoniſt</hi> tries to hide, if not ſmother, this Vice-God, as <hi>Rachel</hi> did her falſe ones, among his Worldly Stuff and Furniture. The <hi>Atheiſt</hi> and <hi>Hypocrite</hi> ſtrive to over-rule its Plea, with Erroneous Principles, and Specious Pretences. But at laſt, when the Conſcience hath thrown off her chains and ſervitude, and aſſerted her rightful authority and dominion over the Sinner (be it in old age or ſickneſs, when he is ſmitten of God or Man) ſhe will change the whole ſcene of affairs; ſhe will ſet up a true light in his ſoul, and give him a juſter apprehenſion of things, and another ſenſe of his own condition; ſhe will pull off the vails and hypocriſies of ſin, and bring her forth in her own horrid ſhape and native deformity; ſhe will tear away the dreſs, and waſh off the Paint, wherewith Satan hath ſet off this <hi>Jezebel;</hi> ſhe will preſent the Sinner with the right end of the Perſpective, which will give him the true image, the full ſize, and the dire proſpect of Divine Wrath and Everlaſting Burnings; which will then prove ſo far from being a <hi>Painted</hi> or <hi>Poetick</hi> Fire, that the meer ſpeculation of them, <hi>i.e.</hi> the very intelligible ſpecies paſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49240:10"/>through a clear underſtanding, will like beams through a Burning Glaſs, immediately kindle a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling raging flame in his Breaſt. One way or other Sin will manifeſt it ſelf to be a Sting indeed, either in the ſharpneſs of remorſe to the Penitent, according to the hainouſneſs of his guilt, or in the prickings and lancings of deſpair to the Obdurate Sinner. What pangs and throws, what anguiſh and torment it breeds even in good Men, may be learned from <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>mourning all the day long,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.6, 3.</note> and having no reſt in his bones, by reaſon of his ſin;</hi> from St. <hi>Pauls</hi> vehement exclamation, <hi>O wretched man that I am;</hi> and from St. <hi>Peters</hi> bitter tears.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</note> And <hi>if it be ſo with the green tree, what will it be with the dry?</hi> If the true Penitent ſuffer ſuch whips, what wonder if the Deſpairing Sinner be laſhed with Scorpions?</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Nam mens ſibi conſcia facti
<note place="margin">Lucret.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Praemetuens adhibet ſtimulos, terretque flagellis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The moſt exquiſite torments will be his perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual entertainment; ſtings and poiſons, fires and furies feed daily on his Marrow and drink up his Spirits, who is both the Malefactor, and his own Executioner; firſt, forging and ſharpening the Knives and Goads, and all inſtruments of pain and cruelty in the dark and ſinful receſs of his mind; and afterward in a cool and ſober reflection, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately ſticking them into his own Soul. It is in vain for ſuch a perſon to expect relief from outward applications, who hath the Wolf within his Breaſt, the <hi>Gangrene</hi> in his Conſcience. Bloody <hi>Nero</hi> may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49240:11"/>remove from one appartment to another; may change his Bed every night, and his Companions every day; but the <hi>Fiend</hi> ſtill haunts him, his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Mothers Ghoſt follows him through all the crouds of Men and labyrinths of Buſineſs; through Solitudes and Entertainments; through the Court and the Camp; the Cloſet and the Theater; making his Face as ghaſtly as the Spectre that occaſioned it; and filling his mind with the diſtractions and black horrours of that place from whence it came; and though he conſulted his chiefeſt Magicians in the caſe, yet he could find no Charm able to lay the Phantaſm, or free him from its importunity. <hi>Cain</hi> may wander from one Climat to another, ſeeking reſt, but findeth none; for ſo long as he carries Blood-guiltineſs in his ſoul, he has not ſo much a <hi>Cerberus</hi> dogging him at his heels, as a <hi>Fury</hi> lodg'd within his bowels; and whilſt that fatal ſting, his guilt, remains, he muſt needs bleed within, languiſh and ſink under Inſupportable horrour and <hi>fearful looking for of Judgment.</hi> Nay let a <hi>Judas</hi> or a <hi>Spira</hi> not only change Countries, but Worlds; when their ſouls through extremity of deſpair <hi>chooſe ſtrangling</hi> (in <hi>Jobs</hi> phraſe) ſeeking to Death for a Lenitive, and running to Hell for ſanctuary; (as if the Rolling in Infernal Flames, would be a refreſhment to them, in compariſon of that more intolerable <hi>Top het</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and the Devils themſelves prove leſs cruel than their own Conſciences) yet in the iſſue they will find themſelves moſt dreadfully miſtaken, for the Conſcience is not to be put off with the Body, but the immortal worm will for ever ſtick to the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49240:11"/>part; and will not ceaſe to gnaw within, when the Fiend lays on without. Thoſe external ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous heats and ſcorchings will be ſo far from calling out, or allaying the internal, that they will rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate and enrage them more, and heat the Furnace ſeven times hotter.</p>
            <p>Beſides, our bleſſed Lord who only lay under the Imputation of ſin, felt greater ſharps, and acuter pains in it, than in thoſe Nails and Thorns and Spear, which pierced not only his Hands and Head, but his Heart; for this Sting went deeper than the Body, and made its way through that into his very Soul; throwing him into ſuch vaſt Extremities, ſuch ſtrange and horrible Convulſions, as exceeded all things, but the infinit demerit of our Sins which occaſioned them. What oppreſſions of Spirit? What heavineſs of ſoul unto death? What dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Agonies? What bloody ſweat did it caſt him into? What vehement and reiterated Prayers?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.39, 42, 44.</note> What doleful Cries under the <hi>Paroxyſms</hi> of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, did it extort from him? And if Imputative guilt was thus terrible and tormenting to the holy Jeſus, what will Inherent be to the wicked Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, when they come to labour and ſtruggle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sin is of that virulent nature, that like an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venom'd <hi>Indian</hi> dart, it not only Wounds, but Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: which appears from two particulars; its quick ſpreading Contagion, and its fatal Influence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is of that ſubtle and quick Efficacy, that it immediately diffuſes its contagion through the whole Man; through all the members of the Body,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49240:12"/>the faculties of the ſoul, and the ſpirit of the mind. It mounts up into the Brain, and fills that with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound notions; it corrupts all the ſenſes, making them the Panders of Vice and Vanity, inflaming the Eyes with Luſt and Anger; and ſtopping the Ears like the Deaf Adder againſt the moſt charming and wholeſom Inſtructions.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 140.3.</note> 
               <hi>It ſharpens the tongue like a Serpent, and lays the poiſon of Aſps under the lips;</hi> ſo that nothing but <hi>Corrupt Communication proceeds thence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29.</note> It breaks out in the hands, in all groſs acts of Violence and Injuſtice. Yea, <hi>from the ſole of the foot, even unto the head, it leaves no ſoundneſs, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but wounds and bruiſes and putrefying ſores.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.6.</note> It ſinks into the inward man alſo; darting its ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom through all the ſecret channels and paths of life; ſeizing the nobleſt appartments of the ſoul, and the chief offices of reaſon. It transforms all its faculties into the powers of Satan; darkening the underſtanding, that it cannot diſcern, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine aright of truth; diſabling the will for em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing and holding faſt what is good; and infee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the memory that it can neither retain, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the notions that are ſtampt upon it. It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the affections and inclinations of the Mind, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Carnal Luſts and Appetites; and infects the fountain of them, the Heart; ſo as to make it ſwell and rankle with all manner of malice and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. In ſhort, it turns the whole Body into a body of Sin; changes that Incarnate Angel, the Soul, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Fiend; and taints our very Spirit, that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Breath of Life, making it ſtink in the noſtrils of the Almighty. Nay Sin is ſuch an exalted <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixir</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49240:12"/>of Poiſon, that the leaſt grain of it is able to tranſmute a whole World in a moment into its Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant nature. Which unhappy Projection hath been actually made already by our firſt Parents, who no ſooner toucht it, but its Rancorous Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment impregnated the whole Maſs of Humane Nature, ſtream'd through all the Blood of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and ſo turn'd the happy Golden Age into this wretched one of Braſs and Iron.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Sin is of a deadly Influence; it may make its entry as <hi>Ehud</hi> did to <hi>Eglon,</hi> with a Preſent in its hand, but will at laſt leave a ſecret Dagger in our Bowels. In a day or leſs it brings forth death;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.17, 21.</note> 
               <hi>In the day thou eats thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely die,</hi> Gen. 2.17. For though Man did not then preſently die, yet in the ſame inſtant he became Mortal; that deadly infuſion was then let into his Veins, and mixt with his Spirits, which was ſure to be his Bane in the concluſion. Whereas, without this, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World could have been deſtructive to us; neither Weapon nor Diſtemper, Bliting nor Thunder; 'tis Sin alone that gives an edge to the Sword, an infection to the Air, and points to the flames of Fire; 'tis this that gives malignity to Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, virulence to Poiſons, and arms every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with inſtruments of death againſt us; ſo that had we not been ſo wretched, as to be Sinners, we had been ſo happy, as to be Immortal. Our naked Innocence would have been greater ſecurity to us, and more impenetrable than a Coat of Mail. Had it not been for this Sting, Death it ſelf could never have reach'd us; no, nor ſo much as had any being
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49240:13"/>in the World. <hi>For Sin brings forth Death,</hi> James 1.15. And though our Saviour (who knew no Sin) taſted of it, yet that was not of neceſſity, but a voluntary undertaking; that as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> by Sin brought Death into the World, ſo he the ſecond by Death might caſt Sin out of it. This is the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Root from whence ſprings all the Miſery, both for degree and kind, which ever befell Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. All the ſteps and advances towards our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſorrow, (from the firſt indiſpoſition and ſlighteſt pain, to final Death and utter Damnation) derive from hence. We were once ſo hardy and firm in our uprightneſs, that nothing could pierce or annoy us; but that unhappy fall that Sin gave us, ſo bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and looſened our Conſtitution, and made us ever ſince ſo feeble and tender, that we are now brought under the power of the weakeſt and moſt Contemptible Creature. The leaſt Fly wants not a weapon to wound us; and the ſmalleſt Kernel hath been the fatal Inſtrument of Death. The Lamp of our Life is now eaſily blown out, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to expire with any extraordinary Paſſions, even thoſe ſoft and gayer ones of Mirth and Joy. 'Tis this that often makes the ordinary means of our health the occaſion of our ſickneſs; and not only faſting, but food, mortal. To this the ſeveral kinds of Death, whether Temporal, Spiritual or Eternal, owe their Original. The wounds which this Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon gives, are ſo fatal, as to deſtroy not only Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but Grace alſo, and Glory; working ſuch a Miracle of Miſchief, as to extinguiſh that Life which is everlaſting. It is ſo dreadful and ruinous, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49240:13"/>it kills the Soul as well as the Body, and ſends not only to the Grave but to Hell. It deſtroy'd the old World of Men by a Flood, laying waſte the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Paradiſial</hi> Earth, and turning it into a great ruine. It ſwept away at once a great part of the Inhabitants of Heaven, arreſting the faln Angels before the Throne of the Almighty, and hurrying them headlong into the bottomleſs Pit; and it will at laſt people the woful Kingdom of Darkneſs wich an unknown number of miſerable deluded Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. There is no ſort of it, whether Original (if its poiſon be not waſhed out in the Laver of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration) or Actual, how ſmall ſoever (if the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per be not cruſhed by Contrition and Repentance) but will prove mortal. One ſingle act of it (if it were poſſible to ſtop there) nay the leaſt omiſſion entitles to eternal Death. That is the wages that will be ſure to be paid us, even for not doing our work. A petty neglect of Charity will deprive us of the inexhauſtible Treaſures of the Divine Mercy, and we may purchaſe to our ſelves a portion in the <hi>lake which burns with fire,</hi> by denying a Cup of cold Water. Not only an idle word; but ſometimes ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence it ſelf conſigns to Damnation. Thus deadly is this Sting, in all its kinds and degrees; which is the Weapon wherewith this Enemy aſſaults us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſucceſs which this Enemy uſually meets with in his Conflict with Mankind, is Victory. If this were not ſufficiently implyed in the Queſtion, <hi>Where's thy Victory?</hi> (As if he ſhould ſay; thy Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory hitherto hath been notoriouſly both known and felt, but where is it now?) yet all Countries
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49240:14"/>and Ages, Hiſtories and Obſervation ſhew how he hath gone on Conquering and to Conquer; what ſpoils and devaſtations he hath made throughout the World; what ſlaughters and maſſacres he hath committed upon the ſons of Men. There was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any univerſal Monarch upon Earth beſides this King of Terrors, to whom all living Creatures, ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or later, muſt bow and obey. The mightieſt Princes as well as the meaneſt Subjects, are his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butaries; he neither favours the Scepter, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets the Spade; but calls for them all in, and piles them up in one confuſed heap, to raiſe a triumphal Pyramid to his name. <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Alexander, Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Tamberlane,</hi> after all their glorious Conqueſts and Trophies, their Temples and Statues, have at laſt let fall their Victorious Arms at the feet of this great Conqueror, and laid down their Heads on the cold Clod, in homage and obeiſance to his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded Empire. Thoſe Heroick flaming Spirits who were ſo fierce and keen for Victory and Honour, and ſo unſatiable with All this World could give them, that they were impatient even to the Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacy of tears, that there was no more then this to Conquer and Triumph over, have yet in fine had all their heat and vigour quenched and tamed by the cold hand of Death; their Glory covered with Darkneſs; and themſelves led in triumph, by this great Triumpher; who might inſult them too in the Prophetick Stile, ſaying, <hi>Is this the Man that made the Earth to tremble,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.</note> and ſhaked Kingdoms? That made the World a Wilderneſs, and deſtroyed the Cities thereof?</hi> How art thou faln from Heaven? <hi>O Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49240:14"/>Son of the morning;</hi> O thou <hi>who didſt weaken the Nations, Art thou alſo become weak like other Men?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.</note> Doſt thou lie among thoſe that are ſlain with the Sword? And bear the ſhame of them that go down to the Pit?</hi> How come thy once glittering weapons of War to lie ſo quiet and ruſty by thee, while thoſe Deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enemies the Worms aſſault and prevail over thee; intrench within thy boſom, and prey upon thy Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals? He was as great a Warriour as a King who acknowledged the Abſolute Soveraignty and general ſucceſs of this Monarch, in asking the queſtion; <hi>What Man is he that lives and ſhall not ſee death? and ſhall he deliver his Soul from the hand of the Grave? Pſal.</hi> 89.48. And not only <hi>David,</hi> the Man after Gods own heart, but the Son of <hi>David,</hi> the Man to whoſe heart God himſelf was hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically joyn'd, the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> was for ſome time his Subject and Captive. Who then can expect an Exemption from walking in this <hi>way of all the Earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet we ſhould the leſs envy him the glory and univerſality of this Victory, if the effects of it fell not ſo ruinouſly upon us. If the overthrow were no more than the greateſt Temporal Deſtruction, nay, (which is greater) than an Eternal Annihilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; (ſo that as our hopes were only in this life, our fears might be of no other) Our Caſe were the leſs Deplorable; We ſhould then, at worſt, be but Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively Miſerable. But when the death of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is but a Prologue to the death of the Soul; and when this ſecond Death is ſo far from being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that it is an everlaſting and unconceivable torment; when it is ſuch a forlorn ſtate, as that the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49240:15"/>greateſt Evil, the utmoſt Misfortune of this VVorld, even Death it ſelf, would be the greateſt Good, and only Comfort; and yet not only the hopes, but the very Poſſibility of Dying, is there extinct; ſeeing it is an Immortal Death: This advances our Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, not more above the Patience, than the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, of the Dreadfulneſs of the Enemy, of the Deadlineſs of the VVeapon, of the generality of their Succeſs, and the neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent thereof, our extream Deſolation may give us juſt occaſion to cry out;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>O wretched Men that we are, who ſhall deliver us from the body</hi> of Sin and <hi>of this Death?</hi> VVho ſhall reſcue us from the All-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Mouth of this Grave? Certainly neither Man nor Angel can deliver us from the force and fury of theſe Enemies; yet from the fear of them we may be delivered by the happy tidings of a perfect Victory over them all, which is brought us by,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond General. The Author and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſs of this Victory. <hi>Sed quis nobis Hercules;</hi> But alaſs! who will venture to go forth and fight this <hi>Goliah</hi> for us, that thus Diſmaies and Defies the whole Hoſt of Mankind, and dares them to match him with an Equal Combatant. Let no Mans heart fail, for there is one who will undertake him, and he though not a <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yet his Son according to the Fleſh; one who hath already gone out, ſmitten, and ſet his foot upon him. 'Tis <hi>Our great Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who came down from Heaven on purpoſe to fight this bloody Battle for us; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49240:15"/>the Liſts with Death and the Grave, and Sin, and all the Black Legions of Darkneſs, who had held us ſo long in fear and bondage. And though his whole Life was but one continued Diſpute with them, yet the ſharp and doubtful Encounter was at his Paſſion, when he was not only ſore thruſt at, bruiſed, and wounded, but ſlain: Not only loſt Blood, but Life too; and his Body cloſely Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned in a Tomb. So that now (one would think) Death might be able to anſwer the Queſtion of the Text to purpoſe; and ſay, Behold here's my Sting fixed in the Body of the Lord of Life; ſee the deep wound it hath made in his Side, which hath let out his very Hearts Blood. The Grave might alſo vauntingly reply, My Victory was in <hi>Golgotha,</hi> and behold here's my Priſoner, whom I have in ſafe Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody in this Cave. But ſtay a while and you ſhall <hi>ſee the ſalvation of the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13.</note> who though he fell to the ground, roſe up again; and that <hi>Antoeus</hi>-like, with renewed force and vertue; when he charged his Enemies afreſh, broke all their ſtrengths, and gave them a final overthrow; when he diſarmed Death of his Sting and quenched its Poiſon in his Blood; and by taking away the guilt thereof, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed both the power and enmity of Death; though he ſuffered the Enemy to continue till the General Reſurrection. He conquered the Grave alſo, making his way through all its Guards and Rampiers: it having no more power to detain him, than the travelling Woman hath the ſtruggling bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of her Womb, when it comes to the Birth. For how was it poſſible that a narrow Sepulchre ſhould
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49240:16"/>hold him, whom neither the Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> nor the <hi>Heaven of Heavens are able to contain.</hi> It was a glorious Miracle for him to open the Graves, to unlock thoſe Chambers of Death for others, when he was alive; but infinitely more to break its Iron Bars aſunder, and throw open its Doors, when he lay Dead, and buried in it himſelf; and to riſe up, and march out, like the Sun in his full ſtrength. A Victory this, ſufficient to father it ſelf, and which viſibly points to no leſs than a Divine Author, and an Omnipotent Arm. It could be no other than our Spiritual <hi>Sampſon, the ſtrength of our Salvation,</hi> who when the Enemy thought him ſure, and ſealed up even to an Impoſſibility of a Reſurrection, awoke thus out of the ſleep of Death, ſhook himſelf, and carried away the gates of his Priſon to the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mount, giving eminent proof of his ability and fitneſs for this mighty Enterpriſe, by beating the Enemy at his own Weapon, and in his own Strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Holds, the Grave and Hell; and all this in the weakneſs of Humane Nature, which had been ſo often foil'd by the Adverſary.</p>
            <p>And yet this Victory was not more Eminent for its Author, nor more wonderful for its Manner, than Compleat for its Effect. It was ſo abſolute, that it not only preſented us with our Capital Enemy in Chains, but extended it ſelf to all its Aſſociates, ſo as not to leave one Adverſary behind, to lift up his hand againſt us. There's no more Condemnation now from the Law,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> to them who are under Grace, <hi>Sin hath no more Dominion over us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ch.</hi> 6.14.</note> though it ſtill keeps a Reſidence among us. Death hath never
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49240:16"/>an Inſtrument of Cruelty or Terror left him, but being diſarmed of his Sting, he is a naked, gentle, and innocent Enemy. He is deſtroyed alſo who had the power of Death, that is the Devil. And now the Serpents Head being thus broken, though his Tail may ſtill move and ſeem to threaten, yet it cannot hurt us. We may ſafely play with the Scorpion, that hath loſt its Sting; for though we may find ſome loathing and abhorrence in our ſelves to it, yet we ſhall receive no harm from it. To die now for Chriſtians, is but to fall into a quiet and ſound ſleep; to renew our vigour for the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Everlaſting and Divine Life, when we awake in the morning of the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>The Grave likewiſe is ſo abſolutely vanquiſhed, that it will not withold one of its Priſoners: but muſt at the appointed time ſurrender up all, both good and bad. Our Saviour hath ſo broken the Teeth and Jaws of this Devourer, that it may ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but it cannot grind us; it may receive us into its Belly, (as the Whale did the Prophet) but not being able to hold us, muſt of neceſſity caſt us up again, upon the Land of Immortality. The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall come forth of that cloſe Cell of Darkneſs and Corruption into ſpacious Regions of Light and Glory. The Wicked ſhall be brought forth too, but it will be to a Bar that will doom them to a far more Diſmal Place: They ſhall riſe out of one Pit, only to fall into another, more horrid and bottomleſs; They ſhall be rouſed out of a ſtate of Inſenſibility and ſtill Silence, to be driven into another of Sharpeſt Senſe, and moſt ſhrill and terrible Shriekings; They ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49240:17"/>enter upon Miſeries which are no more poſſible to be undergone by them, than underſtood by us.</p>
            <p>We may now be able to make ſome Competent Eſtimate of the greatneſs both of the Victory, and of the Mercy to us therein. A Victory over the Enemies of this Life, is valuable to thoſe who have groaned under a Tyrannizing Conquerour; or ſmarted in ſome Bloody Battle. Thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſeem to have fully underſtood its price, who having been long haraſſed by their Enemies, offered to God whatſoever he pleaſed for one; <hi>Do thou unto us,</hi> ſay they,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoever ſeemeth good unto thee, deliver us only, we pray thee, this day.</hi> The <hi>Romans</hi> were not more ſatisfied with any Conqueſt, than with thoſe they had over the <hi>Germans,</hi> becauſe they were ſo near Neighbours, and had been ſo long and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious an Enemy to them. Surely a right apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Enemies in the Text will recommend this Victory over them, as far more glorious in it ſelf, ſo more Comfortable to us. For of Enemies, ſome are Noble and Generous, aiming like <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> only at Glory and Triumph; Others are Imperious and Tyrannical, deſigning (like <hi>Carthage</hi>) Domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Oppreſſion: yet the bittereſt Feuds and Hoſtilities in this World, all Bodily Servitudes, and Temporal Sufferances whatſoever, are perfect friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, freedoms, and Entertainments, in compariſon of that Mortal (ſhall I ſay Immortal) Enmity, that Spiritual Bondage, that Eternal Miſery, which we are delivered from by this happy Victory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. VVhich ſhews the Reaſonableneſs of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing and Rejoycing for the ſame. It was one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49240:17"/>of the Fundamental Laws of the <hi>Roman</hi> Triumphs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Val. Max. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1.</note> that there ſhould be five thouſand Enemies ſlain in the Battle; but that could not debar our Victorious Lord from a right to this Honour, who had vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſlain infinitely more in deſtroying the whole Body of Sin and Death, and in ſpoiling Legions of Principalities and Powers. Wherefore as at his Reſurrection he got the Victory, ſo at his Aſcenſion he Rode in Triumph; when he went up towards the Heavenly City <hi>with a Shout,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 47.5.</note> and the ſound of a Trumpet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8.</note> having the Clouds for his Triumphal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, <hi>leading Captivity Captive,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.15.</note> and making ſhew</hi> of the Spoils openly. When he was doubtleſs met in the way to the upper <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by numberleſs Troops of Angels and Seraphims, with Pſalms in their Hands, and <hi>Hoſanna's</hi> in their Mouths (as the Daughters of <hi>Iſrael</hi> met his Father <hi>David</hi> with Muſick and Dancing in his return from ſlaying the <hi>Philiſtin</hi>) and by them Conducted with the greateſt Magnificence and Jubilation into the Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.8, 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as he hath given us the benefit of his Victory, ſo the honour of a Triumph too; though at preſent in the Inferour Kind. We may have our Chriſtian Acclamations now, proportionable to the Pagan Ovations; and our <hi>Hoſanna's</hi> to anſwer their <hi>Jo Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's;</hi> and that upon better ground then any they ever had, ſeeing by it we are not only delivered from the power and malice of our Cruel Enemy, but alſo from thoſe mighty fears and inſuperable Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions we had of them. He hath diſperſed all thoſe horrours and amazements, that unavoidably
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49240:18"/>ſprung up in our Minds, under the thoughts of our dropping into an Abyſs of Darkneſs, and of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; if not of endleſs and Exquiſite Miſery. He hath releaſed us from that pepetual anguiſh and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, that formerly ſtuck to the Soul in ſpite of all Humane Relief. That ſcorn'd all the powers of Reaſon; and mocked at the attempts of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy to remove it. He hath freed us from two greater Evils than Death it ſelf; the precedent fear of it in this Life, and the diſmal Conſequence in the next; ſo that we may now lift up our heads and hearts with joy, and behold thoſe Inſulting <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians,</hi> our proud and inhumane Taskmaſters, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead on the Shore; or their Carkaſſes floting on the Waves. We may take a new Song in our Mouths, or elſe that old one of <hi>Moſes</hi> with a little variation;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1.21.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath Triumphed Gloriouſly, the Pale Horſe and the Rider hath he thrown into the Sea,</hi> even into the Red Sea of his Blood. Or elſe reſume this Apoſtolical Hymn of the Text in a holy defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thoſe Enemies; upbraiding and boldly challenging them now to do their worſt, and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſinging, <hi>O Death! Where is thy Sting?</hi> Come bring forth all thy Inſtruments of Miſchief, let looſe all thy Plagues and Poiſons, exert thy deſtructive Victorious Power to the utmoſt, and hurt me now if thou canſt; but alaſs thy Weapon is wreſted out of thy Hand, thy Sinews are Cut, and thy Meager Paleneſs is now not more the ſymptom of thy Envy and Malice, than of thy fainting and languiſhing Spirits. O thou great Deſtroyer of Mankind! thou art now utterly deſtroyed thy ſelf. <hi>O Grave! Where
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49240:18"/>is thy Victory?</hi> Keep me in durance now if thou art able; make faſt all thy Priſon-doors, and throw thy ſtrongeſt Chains and Fetters upon me, yet theſe (as in the caſe of St. <hi>Peter</hi>) ſhall all fall off, and the other fly open. O thou Devourer of all Fleſh, thou art now ſwallowed up in Victory thy ſelf, by him whom thou hadſt devour'd. Who can forbear now not only to Sing, but Dance for Joy, who could not forbear before to Cry out and Tremble for fear, under the ſight or ſenſe of theſe hideous Bugbears to the Heirs of Mortality? ſeeing they are now ſo weaken'd and wounded, that there's little left for us, ſave the honour and pleaſure to ſtand upon, and inſult theſe Sons of <hi>Anak,</hi> who lie thus proſtrate before us.</p>
            <p>Let us then bravely deſpiſe and deride Death with all his Aſſociates and Seconds. Let us not ſo far diſparage this great performance of our Lord, as to receive the Spirit of Bondage again, to fear any of them. This would be to blemiſh the glory of his Victory, as if he had left it imperfect; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he was not only an abſolute Conqueror of them all himſelf,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37.</note> 
               <hi>But hath made us alſo more than Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,</hi> through faith in him; and even that faith he gives us alſo, whereby we <hi>overcome the World.</hi> He hath not only ranſom'd us from the Inſolencies and Severities of our Enemies; loos'd our Bands, knock'd off our Shackles, and ſcatter'd our fears; but bids us fly in upon the Rich Spoils, ſeize the glorious Prize; and advances us to the greateſt Priviledges and Perferments. He not only ſettles us in a State of Peace and Security, but of Grace and Glory. He
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49240:19"/>hath not only pluck'd the Sting out of Death, but hath left Honey in its ſtead; ſo that we may ſuck ſweetneſs out of that Strong One,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.14.</note> and find Meat and Manna in that Eater. That which was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as the greateſt Puniſhment under the Law, is by our Saviours Victorious Reſurrection become a real Bleſſing; and under the Goſpel 'tis little leſs than a Promiſe and Priviledge, that <hi>we ſhall all be changed.</hi> It was formerly eſteemed an unhappineſs that we ſhould dye: it would now be one if we ſhould not. We ſhould be forc'd to ſojourn in this <hi>Meſech,</hi> and be confin'd to dwell for ever in theſe Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> were it not for Death, which is the happy gate to Everlaſting Life. Wherefore we have no reaſon to look upon it as Satan's Serjeant, or as our Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner; but as Chriſts Meſſenger, and our Uſher to Glory. <hi>Socrates</hi> his Divinity raiſed him to ſuch a heigth, as to tell his Philoſophical Friend, that his Enemies might kill, but could not hurt him; ſure our Chriſtianity then will enable us to look upon Death, not ſo much as a tolerable Evil, but as the moſt deſirable good, and the greateſt of Mercies: fitter for our Love and Courtſhip, than for our Fear and Abhorrence. So that if an Angel from Heaven ſhould bring us the news that we ſhould never die, we ought to account it as no Goſpel, no good Tid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but rather as an <hi>Anathema</hi> to us. We need not ſhrug at the Grave neither; for that cold and hard Lodging by our Saviours lying there is become as warm and ſoft as a Bed of Down. That place of Stench and Noiſomneſs, ſince this Roſe of <hi>Sharon</hi> was planted there, is more fragrant than a Bed of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49240:19"/>Spices. 'Tis now not a Dungeon, but a Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, wherein the Sacred Duſt (the only Reliques) of the Saints are to be inſhrined, till the laſt Trump ſhall call for them again, to be built up into a new and living Temple for their own bleſſed Souls and the holy Spirit of God to cohabite in for evermore.</p>
            <p>And as we have little cauſe to fear, ſo leſs to love theſe Enemies, or to enter into any ſecret friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Alliances with them any more; <hi>to make a Covenant with Death,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15.</note> and to be at an Agreement with Hell [or the Grave]</hi> in the Prophets ſenſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> to perſiſt in the way of Wickedneſs, and cheriſh thoſe Sins in our boſom, which are both His and Our Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Enemies; which coſt him ſo dear, as his own Blood to ſubdue; and which if they be ſuffered to revive, will be the death of our Souls. Let us have a care that while he hath fought our Battles, we do not thus make war upon him. That would make this Victory over our Enemies, the greateſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of our ſelves; and call for a Lamentation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Triumph. For ſuch a perverſe Requital of ſo great Salvation, muſt proportionably inhance our future Everlaſting Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>What then ſhall we render unto the Lord for all theſe mighty Benefits? Let us light all our brighteſt Torches of Joy and Gladneſs, and kindle all our Sacrifices of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, to this Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and glorious Conqueror, who hath wrought ſuch wonders of Mercies for us, and deſtroyed thoſe our Potent and Cruel Enemies; Let us praiſe him not only with our Voices, but with our Affections; in our Hearts and in our Lives; in Pious Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49240:20"/>and pure Converſations. The grateful Heathens uſed to Conſecrate the Memory of thoſe Heroes who ſubdu'd their Enemies, and freed their Countries from infeſting Monſters and Giants: not only making them their Kings while they were on Earth, but their Gods afterward in Heaven. And can we do leſs to our Victorious General, who hath vanquiſhed ſo many <hi>Abaddons</hi> and Monſters for us; who hath deſtroy'd a greater Devourer of Mans Fleſh than the <hi>Minotaur,</hi> even Death it ſelf, in its own Labyrinth the Grave; and hath quell'd a more terrible Serpent, than the many-headed <hi>Hydra,</hi> even that whoſe name is <hi>Legion.</hi> Certainly then to obey him as our King, and to adore him as our God, is both Rational and Chriſtian. Why ſhould we not Erect a Statue to his Honour (as Victors uſe to have) not of Silver or Gold, or the Work of Mens Hands, but the Divine Image of himſelf in our Hearts, for a perpetual Remembrance? Let us <hi>take the Cup of Salvation,</hi> and ſing Everlaſting Praiſes to this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Lord of Life, who was content once to die, that we Mortals might live for ever: and when by his own Nature, it was impoſſible for him ſo to do, aſſumed ours, to qualifie himſelf for Death for our ſakes. To this Victorious King of Glory, who roſe again to give us the fuller aſſurance of the truth of his preſent, and of our future Victory at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; laſtly, to this Triumphant God, who aſcended viſibly and gloriouſly into Heaven, to ſhew us the way thither, and to take poſſeſſion of it for us; who hath in his Goſpel thrown wide open the Everlaſting Gates of Glory, and expoſed to our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49240:20"/>view all the Riches, the Beauties, and Honours of his Kingdom; that we might behold the glorious Furniture of thoſe Eternal Manſions, he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for us; and the never fading Crowns of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, hung out to edge our Appetites, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our Ardors to be partakers of them, and to ſupport and animate us in all Difficulties and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts in our paſſage to this new <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> To him I ſay, let us give (as is moſt due) all poſſible Praiſe and Adoration, both now and for evermore.</p>
            <p>And it could be no leſs than a firm aſſurance of this bleſſed Victory over Death, and a clear proſpect of this glorious Scene of Immortality beyond it, which fixed this great and good Man (whoſe Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies we are now Celebrating) in ſo ſteddy and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form a Courſe of Chriſtianity in his Life, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him into ſuch a Chearfulneſs and Serenity of Spirit at his Death.</p>
            <p>In ſhadowing out a more particular, though but faint Idea of this Excellent Perſon, I need not bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row any Colour from his Blood; nor reflect any Luſtre upon his Character, from the ſhining Vertues and Noble Acts of his Anceſtors; which have A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned his Family with many Royal Badges of their Loyalty and Eminent Services to the Crown: though the Honourary Augmentation of a <hi>Hand and Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to their Arms, and of the Mannor of <hi>Hanley</hi> with its Franchiſes and Priviledges to their Eſtate, will never ſuffer the brave Atchievements of Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the <hi>Black Princes</hi> Standard at the famous Battle of <hi>Creſſey,</hi> and the taking Priſoner Count <hi>Tanquervile</hi> the <hi>Norman,</hi> (that bitter Enemy to the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49240:21"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch and Nation) to be forgotten; not to mention, that the moſt Noble Order of <hi>Bannerets,</hi> wherewith ſeveral of his Progenitors have been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, ſufficiently proclaim their Martial Vertues and Performances.</p>
            <p>But it being not from an Imputed, but Inherent Worth, that I deſign to tranſmit his Memory to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; I ſhall rather obſerve, that the greateſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of his Anceſtors ſeem'd to Concenter in his Perſon. The ſingular Piety of his Grandfather Sir <hi>Peter;</hi> the extraordinary Charity and Benignity of his Uncle <hi>Francis;</hi> the Conſtancy and Fixed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Religion of his Father; the quickneſs and Gaiety of Spirit of his Mother, with the untainted Loyalty of his whole Line; conſpired with united Rays to render him the more Illuſtrious.</p>
            <p>Theſe hopeful Seeds of Vertue and Excellency being caſt into his Original Elements, were ſo well water'd and cheriſh'd by his Careful and Pious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the firſt Education of his Green Age; ſo Cultivated and Improved by the Liberal Sciences at the Univerſity in his Blooming Youth; and ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined and Finiſhed afterward at City and Court; as render'd him a moſt Accompliſh'd and Uſeful Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman both to his Prince and Country.</p>
            <p>The Natural Talents of his Mind were above the Common Standard. He was Endued with a large Capacity and generous Amplitude of Soul. His Underſtanding was able to penetrate and Maſter whatever he thought fit to turn it to. His Memory ſo faithful as to retain every thing it laid hold on, but Injuries and Vanities. His Judgment ſolid and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49240:21"/>clear. His Apprehenſion quick and ſagacious; and his Will always well diſpoſed, and in a poſture to act, as well as embrace every thing that was good, and praiſe worthy. He had an abſolute Command over all his Paſſions, ſave only thoſe Divine ones, (which 'tis the greateſt freedom and honour to obey) for though there were many things that might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe, yet none could diſturb him. He had no Anger ever ſparkling in his Eyes; no Malice rankling in his Breaſt; no Envy gnawing upon his Bowels. He knew no hatred of any thing but Sin; no fear of any thing but God. His whole frame was ſo mixt and interwoven, of ſo ſmooth and even a Web, that what Philoſophy denies to the fineſt of Bodies, was the peculiar Prerogative of his inward Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>Temperamentum ad Pondus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the happy Acquaintance and Converſe I had with him for almoſt twenty years, I never perceived in him the leaſt Inclinations to any Immoral, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, or Diſhonourable Action. He was free from all guile and diſguiſe both in his Dealings and Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; not uſing to wrap himſelf up in Clouds, the more undiſcernedly to carry on any mean or dark Deſigns. But eſteem'd it below him to diſſemble or diſown what he judged fit to be either thought or done. He was not ſo Complaiſant indeed as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge in himſelf, or brook in others, the Modiſh Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of a Prophane, Unclean, or Abuſive Wit; much leſs the too faſhionable Dialect of Oaths and Maledictions; ſo that none came nearer to St. <hi>James</hi>'s Character of a Perfect Man, the <hi>not offending</hi> ſo much as <hi>in word.</hi> No Pride ſtrain'd his Behaviour;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.</note>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49240:22"/>no Superciliouſneſs diſtorted his Looks; no Cyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Humour ſowred his Expreſſions. But I muſt not ſtand on theſe inferior Commendations; for though a Negative Deſcription be the higheſt we can give of God, yet it is the loweſt that can be given of a good Man.</p>
            <p>His Social Qualities and Ornaments were too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in their kind to be omitted. He had all the Natural Charms and Graces of a moſt winning Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, and a ſweet Converſation; which few that came within their happy Influence could defend themſelves from being taken with. None was ever endued with more Candor and Ingenuity; more Frankneſs and Affability. He affected a Singula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in nothing, but in a ſincerity, and pitch of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue above the Age. In every thing, and under eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Condition, he was ſo eaſie, free, and well pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as made every one ſo too about him; which was not the fruit of any Labour'd Art of Popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but the reſult of his happy Genius: Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Delight being as inſeperable from his Company, and ſtreaming as eaſily and as naturally from him, as Light from the Sun. His Temper and Deportment were ſo calm and gracious, ſo ſweet and obliging; that he attracted the Eſteem and Love; and entertained the Eyes and Hearts of all People. So that in him, if ever that ſaying was really verified, That <hi>none ever departed ſad out of his Company, except that they ſo ſoon departed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He Acquitted himſelf no leſs Incomparably in all his Private Relations: He was the beſt of Husbands to a moſt Accompliſh'd, Vertuous, and Excellent
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49240:22"/>Lady, which he choſe out of the Honourable and Renowned Family of the <hi>Chicheley</hi>'s; and by whom he was anſwered with an Equal Agreeableneſs, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and Conjugal Affection. He was the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt of Fathers to a hopeful and numerous Iſſue; of which the ſurviving ſix Sons and five Daughters, do according to their Age ſhew Pregnant Symptoms of their Excellent Diſpoſitions, and the fair Fruits of his Paternal Care; in their Gentile and Liberal Education; in all things becoming their Sex and Quality; and eſpecially in their ſeaſoning with the true Principles of Honour, Vertue, and Religion.) How cautious and tender he was in Marrying any of them without their full Conſent, their hearty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and free Choice, he put out of doubt to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by raiſing one in himſelf, and offering it as a Caſe of Conſcience; Whether it was Lawful for a Man to bend or incline the Affections of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if Advantageous and Honourable Matches were propoſed; and finding the Negative maintain'd, he reſolved to abide by it. And according to theſe no leſs Prudent, than Indulgent Meaſures, a little before his Death he diſpoſed both his Eldeſt Son and Daughter into very ſuitable and happy Marriages.</p>
            <p>To his Tenants he was a good Landlord, if that Epithet could be purchaſed; either by his ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and kind uſage of them, when he came to his Eſtate, as raiſed an envy in ſome of his Neighbours; or his frequent demanding no greater Fine for three Lives upon an Expired Leaſe, than what he offered to give them, for their ſurrendring up his Lands in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand sagain.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49240:23"/>
            <p>His Friendſhips not being founded on Fancy or Intereſt, but on ſolid Reaſon and Vertue, were du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and generous. He was faithful to his Truſts; of which he had many. True to his Profeſſions and Promiſes; which he held as ſacred and inviolable. Conſtant to his Friend in the greateſt extremity of an Adverſe Fortune; and a ready Miniſter to him in all Offices of Love and Service; a Counſeller in his Doubts; a Comforter in his Diſtreſs; a Pillar in his Weakneſs; and a Pilot in his Danger.</p>
            <p>That he was Maſter of a fair Eſtate, was only his good Fortune, and the praiſe of his Anceſtors; but it was his Commendation, that he was a prudent Manager, and a Conſiderable Improver of it; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the Addition he made to it of that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seignory, the <hi>Parliamentary Burrough and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony</hi> of <hi>Newton,</hi> in this Neighbourhood. His Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Houſe he ſo far Rebuilt and Ennobled (partly in Effect and partly in Deſign, and preparations for its finiſhing) as may well nigh ſupport what was ſaid of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> in relation to <hi>Rome: Invenit La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritiam, reliquit Marmoream.</hi> In the projecting whereof, and of another for Gods Service, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was the chief Deſigner, ſo in Architecture in general he was a great Maſter. Yet the Inward Model of his Houſe, its Government, was no leſs Excellent and Regular, than its Outward Structure. For his Menial Servants, he always made choice of ſuch Perſons, as were Intelligent, Civil and Gentile; ſuch as beſides the diſcharge of their proper Offices, might by their general Courſe of Sobriety and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, by their good Manners and Ingenious Arts;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49240:23"/>and not by any Vice or Vanity; become Exemplary in the Family: and to whom he was a moſt gentle, kind, and bountiful Maſter, according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts. His Entertainments upon Occaſion, were very Splendid and Magnificent; and managed with that great Decorum, Eaſe, and Stilneſs, as if they had been but their Ordinary Meals. How welcom all Perſons were to his Table, hath as many Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes as it had Gueſts: where there was always the greateſt plenty that could be on this ſide exceſs; and which he ſeaſoned with that generous Freedom and Chearfulneſs of Humour, that gave a pleaſant Reliſh to all the reſt. In ſhort, There was ſuch an Affluence of all things, ſo great a reſort of Perſons of Quality, and ſuch a peculiar Port and Gentile Air appeared through the whole Family, that his Houſe might very well be ſtyled a Country-Court, and <hi>Lime</hi> the Palace to the County-Palatine of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe ſome may conceive theſe however laudable Qualities I have touch'd upon, to be but of the lower form, I muſt add, that (beſides that a Prudent Conduct, even in the ſmalleſt Affairs, is a true ſignature of a great Mind) it is not for want of other Subject in him, nor any abatement to his greater Vertues, which eminently ſhone out in thoſe higher Capacities and Stations, whereto he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly call'd by his Kind and Country: being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all proper Endowments for the weighty Debates in the Senate; and for the diſcharge of his Publick Offices both Civil and Military at home. For though there was no Man leſs fond of Buſineſs,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49240:24"/>yet none more fit for it; or who performed his Truſts with more Courage and Integrity: of which he gave ſufficient Teſtimony in a ſteddy and impartial Adminiſtration of Juſtice; in a ſtrict preſervation of the Peace; in a Provident Care for the Poor; in a conſtant protection of Probity and Innocence; and in a reſolute oppoſition to all the bold Vices and Debaucheries of the times; as particularly, in the ſuppreſſion of Schiſm in the Conventicles, of Faction in the Towns, and Mutinies in the Field; and that in the moſt Critical Junctures both of Church and State. In his whole Conduct purſuing the publick good, pointing at thoſe great ends of Government aſſigned by St. <hi>Peter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</note> the <hi>Puniſhment of Evil Doers, and the praiſe of them that do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Love to his Country was not more ſincere and conſpicuous than his Loyalty to his Prince; which waited not (as many others did) till the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Sun, our late reſtor'd Soveraign; but it broke out in the moſt diſmal midnight of a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Uſurpation; when Loyalty was puniſhed as High Treaſon, and Faction rewarded as Meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; when the name of a King was held as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian in the State, as that of a Biſhop in the Church; and nothing was Crown'd in the Land, ſo much as in a Metaphor, ſave only Rebellion with ſucceſs; nor any thing accounted more worthy of Conſecration, than Schiſm and Sacriledge. Even then he engaged in the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Riſing to reſtore his Exiled Soveraign; though being ſurprized by the Enemy, he was prevented from appearing in that unſucceſsful Enterprize, of which both theſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49240:24"/>Palatine Counties, (the Stage of the Action) and <hi>York</hi> Caſtle (the place of his Impriſonment) are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Witneſſes; when in all likelihood he had faln as a Martyr for his Fidelity to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, as his great Anceſtor Sir <hi>Piers Leigh</hi> had done before, for his Loyalty to that unfortunate Prince <hi>Richard</hi> the Second of that name; had not Providence interpoſing by a ſudden and happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the King, left him only in the lower Claſs of Loyal Confeſſors: reſcuing him for thoſe ſubſequent faithful Services he afterward paid that Prince of Bleſſed Memory. For though he was actually in every Parliament during his whole Reign, yet he never joyn'd any Faction in the Houſe, nor ſo much as once Voted againſt the Crown; which ow'd not its riſe to any Court-flattery or Ambitious Deſigns, but to that well grounded Maxim, That the Eaſe and Weal of all the Members, depend not more neceſſarily upon the good Eſtate of the Head, than the happineſs of the People doth upon their Soveraigns Welfare. This Loyalty of his was not mercenary and ſordid, but ſo truly generous and Chriſtian as to keep above the reach of Paſſion, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity, and Intereſt; neither was it of the Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and Unſtable Kind, which diſplays it ſelf no longer than the Prerogative ſhines upon it, or it may ſerve a turn; but it was a conſtant, uniform Church of <hi>England</hi> Loyalty, which is always ready and zealous to ſacrifice every thing to the Soveraigns Service, (let his Religion and Temper be what it will) (be it Eſtate or Blood) ſave only the Cauſe of God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49240:25"/>and the Church; which as they are always <hi>inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo may they be for ever inſuperable.</hi> He was Proof againſt all Diſcontents, becauſe incapable of any Diſappointments. For though his Attendance upon the King and Countreys Service coſt him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thouſand pounds, yet he never deſign'd any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Advantage from either; but proceeding upon the Heroick Principles of Honour, Duty, and Love to both, thought himſelf amply recompenced with the ſatisfaction that ſprung up in his mind from the ſenſe of ſuch worthy and generous Actions. And this is the Triumph of our Loyalty to our King, as well as of our Love to God, to exert them both without ſo much as any proſpect of Reward. Hence it was that he had the honour to be ſo particularly Eſteemed, and Perſonally beloved by the two Royal Brothers under whom he lived, as to be intruſted by them in the greateſt Offices which his choice of a Country Life would admit of; in all which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted himſelf with ſuch ſignal Fidelity, that (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the many honourable and kind Atteſtations of King <hi>Charles</hi> to that purpoſe) his preſent Majeſty at a ſolemn Debate about a reform of the Deputy Lieutenants, when the name of <hi>Leigh</hi> of <hi>Lime</hi> was mentioned, immediately declared, that he himſelf would undertake for that Gentleman. And when in his Royal Progreſs at <hi>Cheſter</hi> he heard of His laſt fatal Indiſpoſition, he gave an evident Teſtimony of his great value and kindneſs for him, in a free Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of his Perſon, and a Pathetical Condo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance for his Sickneſs.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49240:25"/>
            <p>As to his Religion, he was a true Son of that pureſt branch of Chriſts holy Church, the Church of <hi>England;</hi> from whom he ſuck'd thoſe Pious and Loyal Principles, which led him on to all his Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and great Actions. In whoſe Doctrines he was ſo fully Inſtructed, and ſo firmly Eſtabliſhed, and in whoſe Offices ſo well ſatisfied and exerciſed, as to continue fixed in a conſtant and devout uſe of her Liturgy; in a frequent and comfortable par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Bleſſed Sacrament according to her uſage; and in an unalterable adherence to her Communion in all its branches, in deſpite of all the Arguments and Motives both of Friends and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the contrary. For notwithſtanding his near Relation to, his intimate Friendſhip and frequent Converſe with many Conſiderable Perſons of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith in this County; and although in the other, where he lived, he could hardly breath out of a Schiſmatical Air; yet he kept himſelf untaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by either Extream, in all Trials and Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So that the mouth of Envy and Malice it ſelf muſt henceforth be for ever ſealed up, from calling him either <hi>Church Papiſt,</hi> (as he hath been by the one) or <hi>Church Puritan</hi> (as by the other.) And as no Perſonal Conſiderations or Intereſts were able to draw him from the Church; ſo all the Storms and Tempeſts which diſcharged their fury againſt her, had no other effect, than to make him ſtick the cloſer to her, both for her ſecurity and his own; judging it highly reaſonable, to be wanting in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſave that Church, wherein he aſſuredly hoped to be ſaved himſelf. And as the moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49240:26"/>means for that happy end, he daily pray'd for the peace of this <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as he had formerly wept when he ſaw her in the duſt. Theſe two, <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears,</hi> being all the Weapons ſhe allows to be imploy'd in her Defence. And knowing that They ſhall proſper That love her and devoutly tread her Courts, he was a diligent frequenter of that place where Gods Honour dwells; and did not content himſelf to ſit there as an idle and unconcerned Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator (as the manner of too many is) but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his part with ſo much Devotion and Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the Miniſters themſelves, if they equal'd, did not exceed him. And yet beſide his conſtant Attendance upon the Publick Church Solemnities, he never fail'd of his Daily Service in his Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Chapel, nor of his yet more retir'd and ſecret Devotion in his Cloſet; wherein how hearty and ſincere he was, thoſe excellent Prayers and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of his own compoſing for that purpoſe do ſufficiently teſtifie. But conſidering withall, that the Church was not the only place to exerciſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in, but that the whole World was the proper and great Theater whereon its principal parts were to be acted; namely thoſe indiſpenſable Commands of Natural and Eternal Religion, a faithful Service of God and our Generation, in a Prudent, Pious and Moral Converſation: he took up neither with good Words nor good Intentions, being as little ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with a Talkative Divinity, as a Notional Faith; but went on to good Works; applying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to all Real Acts of Beneficence in every kind. To the Indigent he ſhewed himſelf both Compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49240:26"/>and Bountiful; no leſs Chearful than Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in miniſtering to their Neceſſities: ſcarce ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a poor Perſon at a diſtance, but he prepared to meet him with his Alms in his hand, to prevent his being askt for what he eſteemed a juſt Debt, and ſo doubled the value by the freeneſs of his gift. And whom he thus remembred in his life time he forgat not at his death, bequeathing Conſiderable Sums to their uſe, in the ſeveral Towns where he was bleſt with an Eſtate. To the Injured and Help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Perſons he willingly offered himſelf, as a Shield for their Defence from the violence and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the unreaſonable and powerful Man. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Contentions he was ſo bleſſed a Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, that he might well be ſtyl'd the <hi>Civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliator</hi> of his Country. He Compoſed many Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and prevented more; the former by Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the latter by his Awful Authority, his heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Advices, and the peaceable Examples which he himſelf gave in this kind. For in matters of greateſt moment, touching his own Eſtate, he was ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying and forbearing before he complained; ſo earneſt and ſolicitous for an accommodation when injured; and ſo patient in waiting for a friendly iſſue afterward, that he has not eſcaped Cenſure ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times even from his Friends, for departing from his undoubted Right and Intereſt, rather than make any breach with his Neighbours, to the diſturbance of his inward quiet and outward peace. He had a conſiderable Difference under his Arbitration, at the time of his Death, which though 'tis to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented he lived not to finiſh, that the Parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49240:27"/>might have reap'd the peaceable fruits of his ſucceſsful endeavours upon Earth; yet 'tis not to be doubted but he hath met with the happy reward of his good purpoſe in Heaven. This Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirit of peaceableneſs and gentleneſs, of univerſal good will and Charity, was by long uſe ſo incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into his Conſtitution, and become ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to him, that he was willing to become all things to all Men, to do good unto ſome. So that whoſoever had occaſion to make uſe of him, found in him according to his particular Exigence, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of a Friend, the Wiſdom of a Counſellor, the Uprightneſs of a Judge, and the protection of a Patron.</p>
            <p>And if all this were not Evidence enough of his true Chriſtian Piety in general, and of his unfeigned Love and Zeal for the Church of <hi>England</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, we could <hi>ex Abundanti</hi> preſent you with a further Heroick proof of it, in this Pariſh; where he has at his own proper Charges built a Decent and Elegant Chapel, and taken care to Eſtabliſh a Competent Maintenance for a conſtant Miniſtery therein for the Publick Worſhip of God, <hi>Secundum uſum Anglicanum.</hi> Wherein he ſhew'd himſelf no leſs the Son of the Divine, than of the Gentleman; deriving from the former thoſe Pious Affections and Inclinations to edifie the Church in a literal, as his Father had done in a ſpiritual ſenſe; and from the latter, the Abilities to perfect ſo worthy a Deſign. And as by the ordinary courſe of Generation, he made his deſcent from; ſo by this extraordinary Act of Sacred Munificence, he made an aſcent to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49240:27"/>the Dignity and Honour of his great Grandfather Sir <hi>Peter Legh,</hi> who was the ſole Founder of the Parochial Chapel of <hi>Diſley</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Stock-Port;</hi> in which for a better Augmentation of the Miniſters Salary, this worthy Gentleman not only gave Twenty pounds a year in his life time, but appointed the continuance of the ſame after his Death, till his Son ſhould come to Age. Which Magnificent Pieces of Piety afford a noble Example to all Men of Eſtates, <hi>of honouring God with their ſubſtance,</hi> according to <hi>Solomons</hi> Advice,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9.</note> as well as with cheaper ſervices; and will caſt an Eternal Glory about his Name and Memory. This honour of building a Houſe for the Almighty to dwell in, Holy <hi>David</hi> was more Ambitious of, than of being the Founder of the Royal Palace in <hi>Sion</hi> for himſelf and the ſucceeding Kings of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Which though God denied him, yet he diſmiſt him not without both a Commendation and Reward, for his deſiring and deſigning to do it. And that Mans praiſe is inroll'd in the Everlaſting Regiſter of the Goſpel, who loved his Nation and built them a Synagogue.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 7.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the largeneſs of his Heart, and the liberality of his Hand, his conſtant Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and Private Charities; his Publick Expences and Pious Works and Donations: yet at the foot of the Account, at his Death, his Perſonal Eſtate roſe up to ſuch an unexpected heigth, as can hardly be Accounted for upon any other Hypotheſis than that Divine Principle, <hi>That the Bleſſing of the Lord ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth rich,</hi> Prov. 10.22. And that <hi>he repleniſheth the Treaſures of thoſe that love him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.21.</note> when emptied in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49240:28"/>his Service. Accordingly this good Man ſeems to have ſhared in the promis'd Reward of Godlineſs in this life, and that in a higher degree than the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Sarepta;</hi> for while her Hoſpitable Barrel and Cruſe kept at a ſtand only and waſted not, his Wealth by his Religious Disburſements overflow'd,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.14.</note> and like the true Riches of the Mind, improved by uſing; and ſo became an eminent Inſtance and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of that ſacred Paradox, That <hi>there is that ſcattereth, and yet increaſeth;</hi> Prov. 11.24.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, This Excellent Perſon like an unſpotted Pearl, was a Man of many and bright Vertues, without the leaſt ſtain of any known Vice. In whom we found the Loyalty and Charity of a Church of <hi>England</hi> Man; the Piety and Purity of a Primitive Chriſtian; the Publick Spiritedneſs and Magnanimity of an Heroe, with the Zeal and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of a Martyr. All which Vertues were in him ſuch Originals in their ſeveral kinds, as taken apart may challenge our Imitation; but in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction demand our Wonder.</p>
            <p>And now reflecting upon what I have done, in attempting to draw a Character, where 'twas fitter to pay Admiration; as it may appear to be my Crime, ſo alſo my Juſtification; the former for the Eſſay; the latter for the ill ſucceſs of it. For though the Excellency of the Theme may Impeach my Confidence for undertaking it at all, yet it will at the ſame time Apologize for my Deficiency in performing it no better; the worth of this great Man being ſuch, and ſo well known, that it doth not need, though it deſerve, a better Orator. Beſides,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49240:28"/>the great commotion which I feel in my own Breaſt for the particular ſhare I bear in this general loſs hath ſo ſcattered my thoughts, that it ought to be admitted not only to excuſe a negligence of Style and a diſorderly Method, but to juſtifie them too; as moſt proper for an Argument too bulky for the Undertaker; and moſt becoming the tumultuarineſs of that Paſſion which hath poſſeſſed my Soul.</p>
            <p>Having now attended this Extraordinary Man through the more remarkable and Illuſtrious Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of his Life, we come to the laſt dark ſcene of it, that of his Death; which was uniform and of a piece with all the reſt. For as he lived the Life, ſo he died the Death of the Righteous, in the Unity and Communion of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giving the moſt abſolute Pattern of an Excellent Chriſtian in both. This ſad cloudy part he adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the moſt vigorous exerciſe of all thoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Graces, Faith, Hope, and Charity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he had ſo richly furniſhed himſelf in his life time; and of all thoſe other Divine habits peculiar to that ſtate: not only of Patience and Meekneſs, Chriſtian Courage, and an Entire Reſignment to the Divine Diſpoſal, but of Earneſt Longings and Breathings of Soul to be with Chriſt. In all things performing this laſt part ſo gracefully, as when he went off the Stage not only to deſerve the Plaudits of all good Men and Angels to whom he was a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, but to receive an <hi>Euge</hi> and a Crown from his great Maſter, who hath doubtleſs exalted him to a State of full Recompence and Tranſcendent Glory with himſelf in Heaven; to his great and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49240:29"/>Comfort, though to our no leſs great and inexpreſſible Sorrow. His ſetting like that of the Sun (whoſe unlimited influence and bounty he emulated) though it creates a Day and Joy to the other World, leaves us in the Night and Darkneſs of gloomy thoughts for our loſs. A loſs which muſt be beholding to time to be underſtood, and to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to be forgotten in; a loſs that is not confined within the narrow limits of a Family or a Town; within the Precincts of a Hundred, or a County; but tis National and Epidemical; tis the loſs of ſo great and good a Man, that the Gentry could not have loſt a more faithful Friend, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy a more worthy Aſſociate, nor the Country a more Nobler Patriot. Than whom the King could not have loſt a more Loyal Subject, the Clergy a Stouter Champion, the Church a truer Son, nor the World a greater Example of all that is truly generous, vertuous, and praiſe worthy. Yet we ought not only with patience but chearfulneſs to Contemplate and acquieſce in this great Conjuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our loſſes, they being alſo infinitely over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balanced by his gain of that <hi>Eternal and exceeding weight of glory,</hi> which we are all aſpiring unto, and wherewith he is now certainly Crown'd amidſt an innumerable company of Angels, and of the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect in the City of the Living God, in whoſe preſence is fulneſs of Joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>What we have hitherto heard and ſeen, from both theſe Texts, (I mean the Word and Work of God)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49240:29"/>may yield ſome uſeful Inferences, that may reach thoſe who are neareſt concerned in this ſad occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. If it be true, that Death to the godly is now not only a Conquered Enemy, but a real and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Friend; not ſo much a Curſe or a Croſs, as a great Deliverance and Bleſſing; and if we ought to rejoyce and give thanks unto God for the Victory he hath gained and given us over it; then ſurely we ought to be far from murmuring or immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Mourning, when either we, or any of our fellow-Souldiers, are called out to Triumph over this Enemy, and take poſſeſſion of thoſe Conqueſts; as we do in part at Death: But on the contrary rejoyce and give thanks.</p>
            <p>Hence we may inferr a Double Duty. Firſt the Abſtaining from exceſſive ſorrow: Secondly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of moderate and ſuitable Joy.</p>
            <p>Firſt we ſhould hence Learn to Abſtain from Exceſſive ſorrow. The voice of nature in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens granted a Toleration for men to Lament their Deceaſed Friends, and to wait upon them with Tears and Sorrow to their Graves; But ſhe beſtowed her Praiſes and Encomiums upon thoſe only who bore themſelves bravely above it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Philo Vit. Moſis l.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> though mourning was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a Sin, yet ſuch a Defect and Defilement as Excluded them for a certain time from the uſe of holy things. And though Chriſtianity it ſelf hath not Entertain'd ſo much of Stoiciſm, as to cancel all natural affections, and to recommend a perfect Apathy to her Diſciples; yet ſhe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to Limit and Direct their Motions; to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49240:30"/>them their proper Objects, and their due Meaſures. She knows that Love is ſuch a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Cement as works not only a cloſe and firm Adherence, but ſuch a ſtrange Coalition, nay ſuch a perfect unity of the Lovers hearts, that death cannot ſnatch away the one, without Tearing a piece from the other alſo; and ſo leave the ſurvivor under a kind of neceſſity of ſmarting and bleeding for it. She therefore expects, not that men ſhould be inſenſible of their loſs, but only temperate in their ſorrow. She deſires they would not ſhow themſelves ſo much Friends to the Dead, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come enemies to the Living, to God, and to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Hence S. <hi>Paul's</hi> admonition to the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> concerning them which are aſleep,</hi> is not that they ſorrow not at all, but that they <hi>ſorrow not as others who have no hope.</hi> What a great diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and a Reproach would it be to our Religion, if we could not ſhew an equal courage at leaſt with the Heathens under the loſs of Friends, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſuſtained not only with moderation but unconcernedneſs. Could we in truth urge that Argument for our Lamentation which <hi>Rachel</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd for her refuſing comfort <hi>upon the Death of her Children, becauſe they are not;</hi> or did we not really believe a Reſurrection and eternal Life, we might have more pretence for an exorbitance in this kind: but now, ſeeing it appears from what has been ſaid, and all Chriſtians acknowledge that death can have no other force upon a man than was aſcribed of Old to <hi>Gyges</hi> his Ring; not to unmake, but only to make him Inviſible for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49240:30"/>why ſhould we ſo groſly and meanly deny that in our practice, which we ſo openly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly avow in our Creed? and in deſpite of all the evidence of Scripture, and Specious profeſſion of our Faith, by our unreaſonable deſpondency tell the world that in truth we are deſtitute of all hope; that we not only queſtion, but quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of the being, or the well being of the dead. For can we believe that they ſhall riſe again, and yet thus bitterly bemoan them? what ſhould we have done, if God had left them under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Death, without any Reſurrection? nay what ſhould we have done, if we had reaſon to believe that he had doomed them to the ſecond, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting death? we hereby give too juſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Enemies of our Religion, to deride and expoſe our Hypocriſy, and the Contradiction of our Lives to our Principles; and to wound it through our ſides? nay in effect we doe it our ſelves; for every impatient exclamation, is a kind of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt our holy Faith; and every deep ſigh and groan a palpable Mockery and Ridiculing the Article of Eternal life. Upon which conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chryſ: in Heb. c.</hi> 2. <hi>Hom.</hi> 4.</note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> judges the indulgence of immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate mourning at Funerals, ſo ſcandalous as to deſerve Excommunication; and indeed whatever may be the pretence, there's nothing at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom but a deep tincture of Infidelity which gives birth and nouriſhment to this unruly paſſion. For who can believe that the Son of God himſelf died, and yet ſo impatiently lament that any of the Children of men ſhould die alſo? who can beleive
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49240:31"/>that he conquer'd Death and the Grave, roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and aſcended triumphantly into Heaven, and is there ſate down at the right hand of the Father; and yet lye under ſuch diſtractions of mind, when any of our Relations are call'd out of the body to follow him into his <hi>Kingdom.</hi> We doe hereby raiſe an evil report of that good Land, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan;</hi> we diſcover a mean eſteem of that bleſſed ſeat, <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom, whither good men are carryed at death by the Angels; nay we offer an affront to our Saviour himſelf in deploring their condition as miſerable, whom Faith aſſures us to be with him in Paradiſe partaking of his Glories and made like unto him. And hence St. <hi>Paul</hi> who had been rapt up into the third Heavens, reckon'd it a Gain to him to dye and to be with Chriſt. And doubtleſs one aſſur'd thought of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Heaven, one ſingle glance of the Glories where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our Friend is Crown'd, would effectually quaſh and becalm all thoſe ſtormy paſſions, and impetuous commotions of Soul which we ſuffer for him. So that in final reſolution, Immoderate mourning is ſo unchriſtian a paſſion, that it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently betrays our want of thoſe Goſpel-Graces, either Faith in the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, and future happineſs; or hope and Charity; if we bewail our Friend as if he had no ſhare in them. Whereas both his Life and Death were the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt indications to the contrary; for as he liv'd not the common Life, ſo he dyed not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Death of all men, but the peculiar and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing one of Gods Children, amidſt the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteries,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49240:31"/>and in the embraces of thoſe who would willingly have ſacrificed their own lives to have redeemed his; amidſt the prayers of his deareſt Relations, returning them his laſt Counſels and Bleſſings; under the greateſt calmneſs of Spirit, and clearneſs of underſtanding to the Fatal mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his happy Soul being conſtantly exercis'd and inflam'd with the pureſt and moſt ardent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, overflowing with Spiritual Comforts and glorious Expectations, till at laſt it went off as it were in a holy Extaſy on the wings of Divine Love and Heavenly Meditations, into the bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Regions of Light, and Glory, and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly and Laſtly, let us not only ſhut up natures Flood-gates, and quit our ſelves like men; but let us open the Channels of grace, and riſe up to the Dignity of Chriſtians, and to the Example which the great Apoſtle gives us in the Text; by taking up a ſong of Joy and Thankſgiving to God, for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py deliverance and exaltation of our Departed friend. There is nothing more uſual, nor perhaps more natural for human Minds, than in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and inclinations eſpecially to fly from one extreme to another. Mans whole life is but a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Vibration betwixt the oppoſite Paſſions of hope and fear; of Grief and Joy: which are the <hi>Syſtole</hi> and <hi>Diaſtole</hi> of the Mind, Alternatly and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt neceſſarily ſucceeding one another. And Tears are as natural Expreſſions of Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Joy, as of common Sorrow. Let us try then the Experiment in the preſent Caſe, and ſee how
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49240:32"/>happily we can Change the Irrational and dull Paſſion of ſadneſs, into that Angelick and <hi>Spritely</hi> one of <hi>cheerfulneſs and gladneſs of Heart:</hi> By in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging our paſſionate and melting Souls in the Divine and Pathetick tranſports of Joy and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultation with this Triumphing Saint: By Lanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were out of the Body, to fly up after him into thoſe Orbs of Bleſſedneſs above, to be preſent at his Coronation, and to behold how he Reigns and Shines in the Kingdom of Glory. At leaſt let us turn our Condoleances into Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations; Anoint our Heads and put on both Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival Robes and Spirits, at this time of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Inauguration. How unſuitable are our mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weeds, to thoſe white Raiments, with which he is now Array'd. How Incongruous are our ſad cries and Ditties, to his Joyful Hymns and ſweet Hallelujahs. Sure his bleſſed Condition which hath Advanced him above the Benefit, (though ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Addreſſes and Adorations) of our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers is a fitter ſubject for Thankſgiving, than Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. One of the beſt Arguments of true Love is the ſympathizing, in both fortunes, with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beloved. But what a Strange and Ridiculous proof do they offer of their Affection, who break their hearts with Sorrow, becauſe their friend is Tranſported with Joy: who ſuffer their own ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to be the more Dejected, by how much his is exalted? like the Repreſentation of the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodies in the water, the higher the Objects are in Reality above its ſurface, the Lower doth their Image and Counterpart ſeem to ſink beneath it.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49240:32"/>Let us rather Aſcend with him in Divine Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and rais'd Affections, into the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens. Let us Rejoyce with him, who doth now Rejoyce, and Sing with him, who is now Singing a new ſong of glory and praiſe, and thanksgiving to Him that ſits upon the Throne, for the infinite mercy of this his happy Tranſlation. There's none who had any true affection for him here, but would be deſirous to have as much Converſe with him ſtill as is poſſible. Now the only way, and the higheſt degree of keeping up a ſpiritual Correſpondence, a holy Communion with him, is by doing Gods will on Earth, as he is doing it in heaven; by gloryfying our Creator at his footſtool, as he is doing before his Throne; by bearing (though it be never ſo mean) a part in that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Conſort and Anthem of Divine praiſe, which is Maintain'd by the Church OEcumenical; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is ſinging the higheſt and ſweeteſt Notes in the Auguſt Cathedral of heaven. There is Doubtleſs joy among the Angels at the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Saint, as well as at the Converſion of a Sinner; and if there be no Expreſſions but of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row amongſt men on that Occaſion, what is this but to walk directly oppoſite to the Inhabitants of that upper world; and to juſtify this Churches title of Militant on Earth, upon this (if there were no other) reaſon, that it Claſhes with the ways and intereſts of that which is Triumphant in Heaven. Let us wipe off this black Infamy from the glorious name of Chriſtians. Let Atheiſts and Libertines, whoſe hopes Expire with their breath,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49240:33"/>go whining about in the Low and Lamentable ſtyle of Melancholick and Doleful Elegies at the Death of their friends; and of Deſpairing Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and bitter Curſes upon the Cruelty of the Fates. It becomes the Inlightned Race of Chriſts Diſciples who profeſs themſelves heirs of Eternity to make a higher and nobler Flight, and in a generous and heroic ſtrain to ſing a Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Song at the Departure of thoſe, who Die in the Lord; and to Congratulate their happy Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement with a chearfulneſs of Spirit not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to that wherewith they now poſſeſs it. This <hi>which I propoſe</hi> is no Impoſſibility in Nature, nor <hi>Romance</hi> in Divinity; but a practical Myſtery and a Noble eminence of Religion. The loving our Mortal Enemies, and the rejoycing at the Death of our deareſt friends are perhaps two of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt heights in all Chriſtianity; and the latter ſeems no harder a task, than the former. The one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a Reconciling the Antipathies, the other the divorcing the ſympathies of humane Minds. A pitch this, which was oftner Reach'd by the Strength of Nature and reaſon in the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Heathens than the former. The <hi>Thraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> who mourned at the Nativity, uſed to rejoyce at the Funerals of their Friends. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> Celebrated the Obſequies of their Prophet <hi>Iſis;</hi> The People of <hi>Salamis</hi> of their King <hi>Evagoras;</hi> and the old <hi>Maſſilienſes</hi> of their Chiefeſt Friends; not with ſorrowful Lamentations and Cries; but with Feaſts and Entertainments; with Plays and Showes; with Muſick and Dancing; with Songs and joyful Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49240:33"/>as for thoſe who were entering upon great Honours and Preferments. Whereas we run counter to the common ſtream of nature, as well as to the cuſtom and reaſon of thoſe Nations, if at the birth of our Friends, when they weep, we rejoyce; and at their Death when they rejoyce, we weep and lament. And though the Author of nature our bleſſed Saviour <hi>wept for Lazarus,</hi> yet if we allow the
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doluit Lazarum non dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mientem Chriſtus, ſed potius reſurgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol. ad Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras. It. Concil. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letan.</hi> 3. <hi>Can.</hi> 22.</note> Fathers Deſcant, it was not for his death, which freed him from the Miſeries of this world; but for his riſing from the Dead, which would again expoſe him to them. And Religion recommended to the firſt and beſt Chriſtians this more ſuitable and chearful practice of Rejoycing at their friends Death; not only for the Pagans conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that they reſt from their Labours, and all the troubles of this Life; but upon a higher reaſon alſo, that their works follow them, and that they are admitted
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. Hom.</hi> 4 <hi>in Heb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Nazianz. in laud. Ceſarii. Hieronym. ad O ean. Epitaph. Fabiolae. It. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtach. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaph. Paulae.</hi>
               </note> into the Joy of their Lord. For the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church had their gladſome Torches, and joyful Hymns, and Pſalms in their Offices of burial, which they ſung at their Funerals in Teſtimony of their hope in the Reſurrection; and in token that the Chriſtian Combatants, having now Conquer'd, were Crown'd and advanc'd to glory; praiſing and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God for the ſame, taking Comfort to themſelves, and giving Honour to the perſon departed: ſome Footſteps of which Primitive uſage ſeem ſtill Legible in the Cuſtoms of thoſe places among us where Pſalms are ſung all the way while the Body is Carried to the Grave. Antiquity celebrated the anniverſary memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of their Saints alſo, not with the drooping and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49240:34"/>ceremonies of tears and cries, nor in the Mourning habit of Sackcloath and Aſhes; but with the moſt ſplendid Scenes of Mirth and Feſtivity; with the ſweeteſt expreſſions of Joy and Thankſgiving. And Doubtleſs if we had the ſame vigorous faith and hope which they had, we ſhould not fail of ſhewing the ſame ſerenity of brow, and alacrity of ſpirit, upon the like occaſions. This is neither an unpracticable, nor a very difficult province to him that hath learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Live by Faith; to him that not only confeſſes with his mouth, but believeth with his heart this grand Principle in Religion, of every mans being after Death, and of the good mans being happy; nor laſtly to him, who in our preſent Caſe ſhall be ſo juſt as to believe, that this good man, to whom we are paying theſe laſt Offices of Piety, is entred into the perfections and joys of Eternity. Whoſe Glory though it be ſhut up, and ſkreen'd from our eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, yet (as the Sun in an Eclipſe) it opens and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plays it ſelf Illuſtriouſly to them above. Min gling beams with thoſe bright Stars of the Morning, the Angels and <hi>Cherubims,</hi> he is now ſecurely placed in the City of God, actually Triumphing over Death and Sin; for he can now ſin no more, and therefore can Die no more. His Soul may defy them both and ſay O Death! Sting me now if thou canſt; O Sin! Poiſon me now, if thou art able. His Body alſo reſting in hope, may ſay to the Grave; <hi>Rejoyce not againſt me, O mine Enemy:</hi> for though I am faln <hi>I ſhall riſe again,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.8.</note> Though I ly in <hi>Darkneſs, the Lord ſhall be a Light unto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What our Saviour ſaid of <hi>Jairus</hi>'s Daughter is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49240:34"/>true of our Departed Friend, <hi>that he is not Dead but Sleepeth,</hi> or indeed but one part of him ſleepeth, his Body; for his Soul is awake, and ſings in Heaven. Nay he Lives on Earth too; for in many reſpects Death had no Dominion over him. His Fame ſtill Lives, and will for ever, in the Mouths of all good men, that knew him. His Blood is ſtill warm and flows in the veins of his promiſing Iſſue. His vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and the noble Idea of his <hi>great</hi> mind ſtill Lives, and fairly Dawns forth, in the hopeful Heir of his Family; which God grant he may as fully inherit, as he doth his outward Fortune; Or rather may a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion of the Fathers ſpirit reſt upon the Son; that he who Succeeds, may (if poſſible) Exceed him alſo, in all things that are great, and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, virtuous, and praiſe-worthy: That he may grow up to be a ſupport to all the tender Branches, and a Joy to the Diſconſolate Members of that Large family; And that in time he may fill up the great vacancies made by his Fathers Death, in all ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whether private or publick, both with ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to others, and honour to himſelf; and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Ornament both to his Name and Country.</p>
            <p>To conclude with St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Text; <hi>Let us give thanks to God for giving us</hi> and all Chriſtians <hi>the victory</hi> over Death, and the Grave, and Sin, <hi>Through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Let us give thanks to God for this particular victory, which we aſſuredly hope he hath given our Depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed brother over all his Enemies. Let his Dear Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort give thanks to God and Rejoyce, not that the beloved gueſt of her boſom is ſnatched from her;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49240:35"/>but that He is now in the Embraces of his Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and Raviſhed with Extaſies of Divine Love. Let his Dutiful Children give thanks and Rejoyce; not that He who gave them a being in this world, is taken out of it himſelf; but that they had a Father, who in his Life gave them an Example of great vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; and left behind him at his Death, a Name more fragrant than pretious Ointment. Let us all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and give hearty thanks to God, for the great Miniſteries and Comforts which he vouchſafed us in him, during his abode with us, and for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and ſeaſonable Deliverance of him out of the Dangers, Temptations, and Miſeries of this ſinful world; <hi>Beſeeching him</hi> in the Churches excellent prayer, <hi>That of his Gracious goodneſs,</hi> he would <hi>ſhortly accompliſh the Number of his Elect, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten his Kingdom: That we</hi> meeting again <hi>with</hi> this happy Soul, and <hi>All thoſe</hi> other <hi>that are Departed in the true Faith of his holy name, may have our Conſummation and bliſs, both in Body and Soul, In his Eternal and Everlaſting Glory, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
